A Guide to the Philip D. McMaster papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA179
Rockefeller Archive Center
Philip D. McMaster papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1919-1973
Rockefeller Archive Center
McMaster, Philip Duryee
FA179
8 Cubic Feet 17 boxes, 5 volumes, 1 package
Biographical/Historical note
Philip Duryee McMaster, 1891-1973, scientist worked in pathology and microbiology at The Rockefeller University (earlier RIMR) from 1919 until his death in 1973.
[Note: re Dr. McMaster's middle name: In the N.A.S. Biographical Memoir by Walther F. Goebel, "Duryée" is accented as indicated. Following an inquiry by Carol Moberg in connection with the printing of the Philip D. McMaster Lecture program, a check was made of documents in Dr. McMaster's file, (Boxes 1 and 2). No evidence of Dr. McMaster's use of the accented form was found. Mrs. McMaster also told Carol Moberg that Dr. McMaster did not put an accent on his middle name. C. Kopp, 16 April 1985]
Biographical note
1891 Born September 14, Chestnut Hill, Philadelphia, Pa.
1914 B.S. Princeton University
1918 M.D. University of Pennsylvania Medical School
1917-18 Resident Physician University Hospital, Philadelphia
1918 Commissioned 1st Lieut. M.O.R.C.U.S. Army
1919 Fellow, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, N.Y.
1920 Assistant, RIMR
1922 Associate, RIMR
1926 Associate Member, RIMR
1951 Member, RIMR
1956 Member and Professor, Rockefeller University, N.Y.
1963 Member and Professor Emeritus, RU
1973 Died March 20, MT. Kisco, N.Y.
Arrangement note
Arranged in chronological order, within subject.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 M227
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Papers have been presented as an unrestricted gift to The Rockefeller University by Mrs. Philip Duryee McMaster.
The bulk of this collection was received or inventoried: 1973 October-1974 January. One folder (administrative correspondence, box 17) was received or inventoried 1980 June.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: biographical material, correspondence, reports, notes, lectures, manuscripts, and photographs.
Diseases; Medicine, Preventive; Prevention and health; Pathology; Microbiology; Biology -- Research; Medical sciences; Medical research; Life sciences; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University
- Biographical material; personal and official correspondence, 1
  Scope and Contents
  Letters sent and received.
  Arrangement
  Chronologically arranged.
  - Biography; bibliography (Box 1)
    Significance of work (earlier and later editions including draft copies) as written by Dr. McMaster. Identification cards: Civil Defense; Coast Guard; War Manpower Commission; U.S. Naval Receiving Station; OSRD Research Committee
  - Autobiographical notes (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Transcribed from tape as read by Elizabeth McMaster from draft copy by Dr. McMaster. Includes some recollections by Mrs. McMaster Also bound vol. of autobiography.
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    Official also includes snapshots taken by Dr. McMaster demonstrating interest in sailing, early interest in sports, and in nature: also some family snapshots
  - Early laboratory drawings, undated (Box 1)
  - Selected quotations as collected and kept by Dr. McMaster (Box 1)
  - Death: RU obituary and obituary from Princeton Alumni Weekly, 1973 July 3 (Box 1)
    Some letters of condolence and some correspondence between Elizabeth McMaster and RU Library
  - John Bach McMaster (father), 1925 March 10 (Box 1)
    Includes some publications, program of Testimonial dinner; signed typescript of letter 1925 March lo from Alexander McAdie on Benjamin Franklin controversy. Some correspondence in regard to deposit of Papers and work on biography
  - Personal correspondence (Box 1)
    Early letters deal with medical school and career decisions.
    Includes 1914 Certificate of registration as alien in England; 1929-30 appointment from Harvard as Research Fellow in Psychiatry and two letters April 1930 from I.S. Ravdin as to possible interest in a return to the University of Pennsylvania. Correspondence dealing with war-time attempt to form a group for research in aviation medicine with notes on possible subjects for study; correspondence dealing with request for delayed birth certificate. Primarily correspondence deals with matters of family health, housing, insurance, daughter's tuition.
    Includes 1947 Dec. 18 election to New York Academy of Sciences and 1956 letter signed by D.D. Eisenhower on joining Committee of the Arts and Sciences for Eisenhower.
    Correspondents include: Abell, Richard G.; Beck. James M.; Bond, Earl D.; Boots, Ralph H.; Bronk, Detlev W.; Hektoen, L.; Hoagland, Charles L.; Hogeboom, G.H.; Krumbhaar, Edward B.; Lewis, Paul Adin; Lewis. William Hall; Opie, Eugene L.; Pearce, Richard Mills; Ragle, B. Harrison; Ravdin, I.S.; Richards, A. Newton; Rockefeller, David; Taylor, Harden F.
    Letters of congratulation on becoming Member of RIMR from: May Dwight, Frank Horsfall, Jr., Duncan MacInnes, Henry Parsons, W.J.V. Osterhout, Walter A. Jacobs, Robert A. Moore, John Kidd, Albert Casey, Philip Levine, D.W. Woolley.
    Goebel, Walther. "Biographical Memoir," National Academy of Sciences, v. 50 (1979) 287-308 (2 copies).
    - 1915-1952
    - 1953-1972
- Personal items; official correspondence, 2
  - Personal items; official correspondence (Box 2)
    - Princeton Class of 1914. Primarily Princeton University Foundation 1952-1956, 1914 1952-1956
    - National Academy of Sciences, 1952-1970
      Includes typescript signed letter, 1962 Jan. 1 from Detlev Bronk on future role for President of the Academy.
    - Peyton Rous portrait
      Letters covering contributions from Rufus Cole, Simon Flexner, John Northrup, Eugene L. Opie, Frank Horsfall, Alfred E. Cohn.
      Includes copy of remarks sent to Sir Christopher Andrews on work done with Rous.
    - Letters of recommendation/Condolence letters
      Primarily recommendations for membership in the Century Club and Riverside Yacht Club. Condolence letters are drafts and recipients not always clear. Some recommendations for Heart Association Career Fellowships. Recommended for grants are: Boehme, Diethelm; Drury, Douglas R.; Harris, T.N.; Zweifach, Benjamin W.
    - Laboratory worker: Heinz Kruze, 1942-1962
      Includes old time sheets and cancelled checks on money loaned.
    - Laboratory associates
      Miscellaneous material including correspondence, recommendations and condolences. Letter from R.J. Bachvaroff is summary of laboratory experiences.
      Arrangement note
      Arranged in alphabetical order: Bachvaroff, R.J.; Carter. Thelma; Gaghan, William J.; Kopech, G. (Mrs. Franzl); Leckband, Eva (Wolfe); Marchalonis, John; Morello, Josephine; Moser. Lawrence; Nikitovitch, Miroslava; Pomarico, John; Primosigh Joseph V.; Strum, Ernest; Szutu, Gloria; Van Cleve, James.
    - Laboratory assistant: Joshua Edwards. Correspondence, 1952-1956
    - Laboratory assistant: Robert Franzl, 2 folders
      Grants, reports of work done and manuscripts of published work or presentations.
    - Administrative correspondence, 1935-1972
      Includes some form announcements and 1952 Apr. 2 letter from David Rockefeller and 1952 May 20 copy of reply on future direction of RI on retirement of Herbert Gasser. Photocopy of 50 year certificate from RU 1969 Apr. 8, 1969 October reply to Frederick Seitz on outstanding "alumni" of laboratory and University and accomplishments.
- Correspondence, 1914-1959; 3
  - Correspondence, 1914-1937 1938-1941 1942-1948 1949-1951 1952-1955 1956-1959 (Box 3)
    Letters sent and received. Consists of exchange of scientific information, requests for reprints and explanations of some laboratory techniques; invitations to serve on committees, requests for opinions on submitted manuscripts or grant requests; requests to prepare articles or present papers, sponsorship of papers, academic recommendations or award recommendations.
    Correspondence arranged chronologically include: Abell, Richard; Abramson, Harold A.; Aronson, Joseph D.; Aub, Joseph C.; Batty, Irene; Beard, Joseph W.; Behney, Charles; Benishek, Maria S.; Birkhaug, Konrad E.; Blalock, Alfred; Blankenhorn, M.A.; Bukantz, Samuel C.; Burch, G.E.; Coca, Arthur F.; Coggeshall, L.T.; Coons, Albert H.; Cope, Oliver; Cotzias, G.C.; Cowdry, E.V.; Custer, R.P.; Cutler, John; DeBakey, Michael; Drinker, Cecil K.; Drury, Douglas; Dulaney, Anna Dean; Eagle, Harry; Ebert, James D.; Edwards, Joshua; Ehrich, William; Elman, Robert; Engel, George L.; Farr, Lee E.; Fanchini, Joseph; Freund, Jules; Friedenwald, W.F.; Fulton, J.F.; Furcolow, Michael L.; Gabrieli, Elemer; Gates, Thomas; Goffman, John; Gowans, J.L.; Graham, Evarts A.; Griffith, John Q.; Harris, T.N.; Hertzman, Alrick B.; Himwick, Harold E.; Hinsey, Joseph C.; Homans, John; Hopkins, J.G.; Hudack, S.; Humphrey, J.H.; Irwin, John W.; Ivy, A.C.; Kern, Richard A.; Kukita, Kazuko; Landis, Eugene M.; Langevoort, H.L.; Latta, Harrison; Lederberg, Joshua; Lowenberg, Eugene L.; Luck, J. Murray; Lurie, Max B.; Lyon-Caen, L.; McLean, Douglas; Maddock, Stephen; Miles, A.A.; Minot, George R.; Moon, V.H.; Morgan, Herbert R.; Parks, Edwards A.; Parsons, Robert; Raffel, Sidney; Ragle, B. Harrison; Raddin, I.S.; Rees, Leslie W.; Robertson, J.S.; Salin, Lothan; Samter, Max; Scheibel, Inga; Schlesinger, R. Walter; Schmidt, Carl F.; Selye, Hans; Small, H.A.; Smith, F.; Smith, H.P.; Sutliff, W.D.; Taliaferro, William H.; Thorbecke, G.J.; Voigt, Wilhelm; Wade, H.W.; Walker, Leonard A.; Walser, MacKenzie; Wangensteen, Owen H.; Weech, A.A.; Wertheim, A.R.; Wolbach, S. Bert; Wright, Irving Sherwood; Zweifach, Benj. W.
- Correspondence, 1960-1970; 4
  - Correspondence, 1960-1970 (Box 4)
    - Special techniques
      Notes and protocols for staining techniques, preparation of dyes; production of antibodies; to make Saline Formalin; technique for peritoneal exudate; Feulgen reaction
    - Notes on literature searches
      Notes on and questions concerning techniques and results reported in published literature. Subjects include antibody formation, antigen tracers, aviation medicine, blood proteins, and the anamnestic reaction, corisone effects, sea sickness, skin absportion, spreading factors, trigger mechanisms.
    - Notes on ideas found in published literature
      Includes ideas for experimental follow-up.
      Filed as found but not labeled, sorted, or arranged.
- Budgets and Reports to Director, 5
  Chronological
  - Budgets and Reports to Director (Box 5)
    - Budgets, 1952-1966
      Consists of correspondence, special requests and allowances and budget sheets.
    - Animal House Committee
      Includes reports on minimum and optimum standards for care of laboratory animals; correspondence from faculty and copy of remarks made by Dr. McMaster 1958 January 6 meeting of "Animal House Committee".
    - Notes on Reports to Director, undated
      No arrangement.
    - Reports to Director
      - 1933-1941
      - 1942-1945
      - 1946-1949
      - 1950-1954
      - 1955-1956
      - 1957-1967
      - War work research period with Dr. Gasser, 1937-1938 1942-1945
        Consists of some final forms but primarily first drafts handwritten and edited copies.
        Includes also draft of 1937-1938 illustrated report made to the Corporation.
- Laboratory records and notes on experiments, 1932-1946, 1936-1950, 1951-1953, 1953-1963; 6
  Some folders also include literature references and notes regarding points for discussion, for reports or for papers.
  - Laboratory notes, 1932-1946 (Box 6)
    Records of experiments recorded on cards. Many with photographs (prints and negatives) and some slides.
  - Laboratory records and notes, 1936-1950
    - Data on sections, 1936-1950 (Box 7)
      Includes normal; human albumin transfer; plain albumin transfer; duration of antigen in serum.
    - Pressure of injection and protocol, 1936-1939 (Box 7)
    - Color experiments - horse serum, 1940 (Box 7)
    - Rate of lymph flow in rabbit ears and thermocouple readings, 1941-1942 (Box 7)
    - Studies on burns 1941-1942 Report 1946-1947, 1941-1942 1946-1947 (Box 7)
    - Dyes in patient, 1947 (Box 7)
    - Local hypersensitivity, 1947-1948 (Box 7)
    - Final Color experiment, 1941 September-December (Box 7)
    - Persistence of antigen and active anaphylaxis Series I-II, 1949 June-1950 June (Box 7)
      Includes attempt to use Dr. Dole's photoelectric cell (discarded) 1949-1950.
    - Titration of ear reactions to HA (Human Albumin), 1950 April-June (Box 7)
    - Persistence of antigen and antibody in HA color I (Box 7)
    - Swiss mice series for optimum "shocking dose", 1949, for intraperitoneal test; for anti pneumococcus serum; for horse serum, 1950, 1949-1950 (Box 7)
  - Laboratory records and notes
    - Cells vs Plasma; transfer of plain human albumin and or E-AP-H dye protein, 1950 September-1951 April (Box 8)
    - Antigen vs liver, 1951 July-December (Box 8)
      Includes readings by Merrill Chase and some notes of work done by son of P.D. McMaster called "Palook's exp.".
    - Antigen in mouse blood. BRVR Exp. 1-35, 1951 September-October (Box 8)
    - Transfer of antibody, 1951 August-September 1955 (Box 8)
      Includes experiments on non-precipitating antibody, 1955.
    - Drop in passive reversed anaphylaxis, 1951 October (Box 8)
    - EVR tests with fractionated anti-sera, 1951 November-1952 January (Box 8)
    - Liver vs spleen persistence of T-1824 vs. E-AP-G, 1951-1952 (Box 8)
    - Liver vs spleen by EVR, 1952 January-May (Box 8)
    - Use of active EVR-AnaS response for persistence of antigen, 1952 April-June (Box 8)
    - Serotonin experiments 1-15, 16-23, 1952 May-June (Box 8)
    - Rabbit Liver transfers, 1951-1953 (Box 8)
    - Rabbit serum transfers, 1953 (Box 8)
    - Adrenalectomy, 1952-1953 (Box 8)
    - Swiss mice controls, 1953 January-February (Box 9)
    - Hyper-immunized Mice E-AP-G, 1952-1953 (Box 9)
    - Hyperimmunity notes, discussion, checks to be run (Box 9)
    - Antigen for challenge, 1953 October-November (Box 9)
    - COIR (Cause of Injection Reaction), 1953 September-December (Box 9)
    - Active anaphylactic shock, 1953 March-1954 January (Box 9)
    - Sensitivity of mouse transfer test for antibody, 1955 January-July (Box 9)
      Includes Apr. 1955 experiment for non-precipitating antibodies.
    - Cortisone experiments. History of G series Recipients and donors, 1954-1956 (Box 9)
    - Secondary response Decadron (SRD) 1959 Dec.-Jan. 1961 Secondary response to intra peritoneal particulate antigen under the influence of Decadron, 1959 December-1961 January (Box 9)
    - Endotoxin; Comparison of intra venous and intra peritoneal methods in spleens and nodes; L-K phenomena, 1960-1963 (Box 9)
- Talks, lectures, symposia, 7
  Staff meeting presentations; student talks; lectures and symposia.
  Handwritten and typewritten drafts and correspondence concerning arrangements.
  - Group of handwritten notes of materials presented at staff meetings and later used for student talks (Box 10)
    Includes introduction notes for Cecil Drinker's Harvey Lecture, notes for presentations of various talks where prepared paper not needed. Subjects include: urobilin, interstitial pressures, spread of dye with or without pressure or obstruction, human cutaneous phenomena, persistence of antigens, liver lymphatics, bile flow and anti-viral properties.
  - Miscellaneous notes and outlines used on assorted occasions, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Material for student talks, 1 folder (Box 10)
    Includes transplantation immunity, tracer antigens, sites of antibody formation, mechanism of antibody formation.
  - Drafts and corrected copy of three lectures to Florida students, 1956-1959; 3 folders (Box 10)
    Includes notes as used at various times with pages added and omitted 1956-1957 Florida talks finally presented in 1959.
  - Albany talk: Gall bladder and bile, undated (Box 11)
    Handwritten notes.
  - Harvey lecture "Lymphatic Participation in Cutaneous Phenomena", 1942 April 16 (Box 11)
    Includes typescript copy; typescript of notes for lecture, reprint and glossy photos used and correspondence.
  - Memorial Hospital meeting on "H", 1942 November 20 (Box 11)
    Typescript of corrected remarks
  - Conference on Lymph, New York Academy of Sciences, 1945 April 13-14 (Box 11)
    Correspondence dealing with arrangements for conference made by Dr. McMaster and copy of preprinted manuscripts.
  - Roger Morris Memorial Lecture. Academy of Medicine of Cincinnati, "The Lymphatics of the Skin in Defense of the Body against Injury and Infection", 1948 March 2 (Box 11)
    Includes correspondence with M.A. Blankenhorn on arrangements and handwritten note to P.R. (Peyton Rous?) after the event.
    Includes handwritten notes and some typewritten material.
  - American College of Allergists, "Anaphylactic Shock in Mice Induced by a Traceable Colored Antigen", 1948 March 13 (Box 11)
    Includes correspondence on arrangements, typescript notes and typescript carbon of manuscript as it appeared in JEM.
  - American Assoc. of Immunologists Symposium, "Site of Antibody Formation", 1948 March 17 (Box 11)
    Includes correspondence as chairman with participants also notes for introductory presentation.
  - Dupont Medical Meeting, "Some Activites of Lymphatics of the Skin", 1948 October 26 (Box 11)
    Includes correspondence and carbon typescript summary of remarks.
  - New York Academy of Sciences, "Physiological Conditions existing in Connective Tissue", 1948 December 3-4 (Box 11)
    Includes notes for presentation.
  - Society of American Bacteriologists, "Sites of Antibody Formation", 1950 May 14-18 (Box 11)
    Includes correspondence and carbon typescript "without last minute corrections".
  - New York Academy of Medicine Symposium, Nature and Significance of the Antibody Response. "Sites of Antibody Formation", 1951 March 21-22 (Box 11)
    Correspondence, notes and carbon typescript of chapter in volume edited by A.M. Pappenheimer
  - American Assoc. of Immunologists, "Labeled Antigens and Antibodies", 1951 April 29-May 3 (Box 11)
    Includes correspondence and typescript notes for presentation.
  - National Institutes of Health Symposium, 1961 March 31 (Box 11)
    Conference on recent advances in the knowledge of adrenocortical hormones: "Effect of Adrenocortical Steroids upon Antibody Formation" Correspondence, notes for talk, holograph notes on laboratory work, typescript carbon of manuscript for Metabolism
  - Princeton University Class of 1914, "Medical Progress since 1914: Here Today! Gone Tomorrow? " Handwritten notes and draft, 1962 January 19 (Box 11)
  - Peyton Rous Memorial Address, 1970 May 19 (Box 11)
    Photocopy of address; carbon typescript of report on work of McMaster with Rous; handwritten notes and drafts, handwritten drafts of condolence letter to Mrs. R., some letters regarding address.
- Manuscripts, 8
  Arranged chronologically.
  Handwritten and typewritten drafts of publications. Some include laboratory procedures or materials.
  - Early manuscripts, "Some Causes of Biliary Infections" and "Studies on Urobilin", undated, 1922-1923 (Box 12)
    including 1922-23 photographs of liver, charts and graphs
  - Agglutinen Formation within the Lymph Nodes of Resistant and Susceptible Mice, 1934 (Box 12)
    Typescript, Hudack/McMaster
  - "Relation of the Glucose Requirement to the Toxic Symptoms of Liver Deprivation.", 1934; Typescript Drury / Mc Master (Box 12)
  - Tables photographs, handwritten notes for work done under OSRD contract, 1942-1945 (Box 12)
  - Assorted drafts, typescripts and handwritten charts and tables of Color papers before dividing into two papers (Box 12)
  - "Peripheral Vascular Reactions in Anaphylaxis of the Mouse", 1949; typescript (Box 12)
  - "Distribution and storage of blue antigenic azo proteins in the tissue of mice.", 1949; typescript and edited typescript draft (Box 12)
  - "James Bumgardner Murphy" a memorial prepared for the Century Club., 1950; Typescript (Box 12)
  - Persistence in mice of certain foreign proteins and azo protein tracer-antigens derived from them"., 1951; Typescript carbon, draft copy (Box 12)
  - "Active anaphylaxis to a foreign protein., 1955; Typescript carbon draft copy (Box 12)
  - "Impairment of the antigenicity of a protein antigen follow-its injection into rabbits.", 1957; Typescript carbon draft copy (Box 12)
  - The behavior of two foreign protein antigens in mice during inhibition of antibody formation by cortisone", 1957; typescript carbon copy (Box 12)
  - Florence Rena Sabin; a biographical memoir" written for National Academy of Sciences, 1960 (Box 12)
    Includes typescript carbon, report on retirement dinner, copies of obituary and memorial material, correspondence with co-author, Michael Heidelberger, D.S. Bluemel. Also correspondence with former students and associates.
  - "Antibody formation", 1961; 4 folders (Box 13)
    4 folders of literature notes, drafts and typescript carbon copy of manuscript for chapter in The Cell v. 5, edited by J. Brachet and A.E. Mirsky, 1961.
  - "Effect of bacterial lipopolysaccharides on hemolysin formation in mice.", 1961; Typescript carbon copy (Box 13)
    Franzl/McMaster
  - "The primary immune response in mice, I", 1968; Typescript carbon copy with mounted photographs for figures (Box 13)
  - "The primary immune response in mice, II", 1968; Typescript carbon copy with various drafts when originally submitted as three papers (Box 13)
- Laboratory photographs, 9
  - Rous and McMaster, 1928-1930 (Box 14)
    Glass negatives of laboratory photographs.
    Includes Rous work on "Gradiant of vascular permeability" and McMaster work on "Lymphatics".
  - Card file, 1929-1930 (Box 14)
    to Rous and McMaster glass plates
  - Electron micrographs, 1947 (Box 14)
  - Mounted photographs and illustrations used in talks, 1 folder (Box 14)
  - Photographs, 1931-1964 (Box 15)
    Prints, some negatives, some items have information on photographic technique.
  - Leica film on hairing, 1 roll (Box 15)
  - Mouse Ear shock movie, 2 reels 16 mm (Box 15)
  - H series nos. 50-250, 1 roll of film (Box 15)
  - Information on photographic techniques, 1 folder (Box 16)
  - Mounted photos returned from Publisher (Box 16)
  - Photos used for talks and demonstrations (Box 16)
  - Photos used for chapter on "Antibody formation" (Box 16)
- "Collected Works", 5 bound volumes
- Photographs; University of Pennsylvania "Distinguished Senior Alumnus" citation, 1 package containing oversize photographs and citation. (Package 1)
- Administrative correspondence, 1952-1973; 1 inch (Box 17)
  It is comprised of Correspondence between Dr. McMaster, Dr. Gasser, Dr. Bronk and Dr. Seitz. A few items are with other administration personnel and several letters are from Mrs. Elizabeth McMaster in setting up a lectureship fund in memory of her husband.
  Several letters are concerned with provision for Dr. Franzl's situation when Dr. McMaster becomes Emeritus until Dr. Franzl decides on an appointment elsewhere.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Added in June 1980 from the Office of Faculty and Student records.
  Arranged in chronological order.